なんば　むった
＜私達 宇宙飛行士候補生の➡
The next astronaut candidate training exercise is the Comeback Competition.
次なる訓練は｢カムバック
コンペティション｣への挑戦｡➡
It's a contest where you compete to reach the goal
パラシュートの展開システムや
自動制御のローバーを作り➡
どのぐらい正確にゴールに
たどり着けるかを競う大会だ＞
by building everything from the parachute deployment system to the rover.
(六太)タイヤをスポンジで作ろう｡
We can make the tires out of sponge!
《何!?考えたこともなかった…》
What?
I never considered that!
で 次はパラシュートだけど…｡
Next comes the parachute.
う～ん…パラシュートの…➡
I'm willing to give you one piece of advice about the parachute.
｢パ｣ぐらいは
教えてやってもいいかな｡
(ビンス)何してるんです？
What are you doing?
Well,
ああ いや…ピコに誘われまして…
酒に付き合えって｡
Pico invited me to have a drink with him.
ピコが…君をですか？
ええ｡何故だか僕だけ｡
Pico invited you?
For some reason, I was the only one.
しんぼう
《あと５日｡あと５日の辛抱だ｡➡
Five more days.
I just have to deal with this for five more days...
ヒビト達を乗せたオリオンが
５日後に帰ってきて…➡
In five days, Hibito and the other astronauts will return in Orion.
パラシュートが
バッと開いた瞬間…》
The moment the parachutes deploy...
《ようやく俺は解放される…》
I'll finally be free.
I'm going to speed up.
スピードを少し上げますよ｡
SPACE BROTHERS
You've always been in my heart
But you don't say a thing or even smile
We've always been together
We're ignorant, but we believe
All the time I spent with you
Felt like a dream
We connected the stars and drew pictures
To our hearts' content
Let our hearts, shivering in excitement,
Use the sky as a canvas
And merge to form an everlasting image
#58 Earnest Failure
Watch how the pieces spread.
見ろよ あの広がった破片｡
爆発の規模がわかるね｡
That indicates the explosion's size.
くっそ～！今度こそ上手くいくと
思ってたのに…➡
Man...
I was so sure this one would work.
There goes our rocket, Penguin 14...
俺らのロケット
ペンギン１４号…｡
Stop crying, Pico.
(リック)そう泣くなよ ピコ｡
泣いてねえよ｡
I'm not crying.
ま これはこれで
いい経験になったとしとこうぜ｡➡
Anyway, this was a good experience.
本気の失敗には…価値がある｡
次こそ俺らのロケットは➡
An earnest failure has meaning.
Here's hoping that our next rocket succeeds.
成功するっていう願いをこめて｡
Let's cut this up for souvenirs!
これ 切り分けて持っとこうぜ｡
現在
《平気なのか？》
He isn't panicking?
《こいつ…想像していた
リアクションと違う》
Well...
This isn't the reaction I expected.
《この感じ…➡
Yeah...
突然 人を車に乗せ
猛スピードで走り出す…➡
I was told to hop in, and then he sped off...
２度目だよ こんな目に遭うの》
It's the second time this has happened.
Want some candy?
⦅あんたもキャンディなめるか？
ハハハハ…ブッ！⦆
《でもまあ あの
デニール･ヤングに比べれば…➡
Yeah, compared to Deneil Young,
ビンスさんは だいぶ安全運転》
Vince seems much safer.
《なんとも紳士的な
スピード違反だぜ》
After all, he's barely breaking the speed limit.
ミスター･ナンバ 今は２人だけの
会話だ｡正直に答えて下さい｡
Mr. Nanba, this conversation is to stay between us.
I'd like you to give me an honest answer.
Whom would you consider your enemy?
君にとっての敵は誰ですか？
My enemy?
敵…ですか？
あ～ 敵…え～ 敵…え～っとぉ｡
(ビンス)私にとっては…➡
Enemy... Uh, enemy...
Let's see...
I think of the media as my enemy.
マスコミが敵です｡
彼らの大多数が➡
Most pay little attention to space development and manned spaceflight.
｢宇宙開発｣｢有人飛行｣を
長い目で見てくれない｡➡
Until space development yields tangible results through manned spaceflight,
有人飛行による宇宙開発の
明確な成果を見せない限り➡
they will continue to criticize those of us who are astronauts.
我々 宇宙飛行士の存在を
批判し続ける連中です｡
他にも敵は大勢います｡➡
There are other adversaries.
Scientists who advocate unmanned spaceflight,
無人機のみの宇宙開発を提唱する
科学者連中 ﾛﾎﾞｯﾄ業界 それから…｡
the robotics industry, and
天文学者｡
astronomers.
They frequently complain that manned spaceflight programs are hogging government funding.
彼らは皆 国の予算が有人飛行に
多く使われることに反対し➡
口をそろえて こう訴えます｡➡
科学的成果が得られるのは
我々の仕事だ｡➡
That since the astronomers produce scientific accomplishments,
それができない有人飛行に
大金をまわすのは➡
the money spent on manned spaceflight is being wasted.
全くのムダ遣いだと｡
君は履歴書のプロフィールに
尊敬する人物として➡
You listed an astronomer's name as one of the people you respect.
天文学者の名前を
書いていましたね｡
ああ…はい｡
Y-Yes.
I cannot understand why.
理解に苦しみます｡
Uh, Sharon isn't like that...
いや シャロンは全然そんな…｡
(ビンス)いいですか
ミスター･ナンバ…➡
Listen to me, Mr. Nanba.
人が宇宙に行ってこその
宇宙開発だ｡
The purpose of space development is to send humans into space.
私は そう信じています｡➡
That is what I believe.
我々の邪魔をするものは皆
敵です｡
Anyone who tries to stop us is our enemy.
The three astronauts that have landed on the moon are now moving toward Moonbase.
[TV]月面に到着した３名の飛行士は
基地への移動を開始しました｡➡
彼らの乗るロシア製月面車
スコールイは➡
They are riding aboard the Russian lunar rover Shkvali at a speed of thirty kilometers per hour.
現在時速３０キロで走行｡➡
まもなく月面基地に到着する
予定となっています｡
They will arrive at Moonbase shortly.
早く着きすぎましたね｡
It would appear we're early.
そうっすね｡
Indeed.
Well, you're the one who drove so fast.
《そりゃそうだよ｡
あれだけ飛ばせば》
あの ビンスさん…
さっきの話なんですけど｡
Uh, Vince...
About what you were saying before,
俺にとっての敵が
誰かっていう｡
はい｡
you asked whom I'd consider my enemy.
Yes.
衛星やロボットの開発者も
技術者も➡
You have the engineers who work on satellites and robots,
the astronomers and scientists,
天文学者も科学者も…➡
それから宇宙飛行士も｡
and naturally, the astronauts.
We all love space, so aren't we all on the same side?
みんな宇宙が好きでやっている
人々だから➡
いいんじゃないですかね
仲間ってことで｡
じゃあ 君には敵はいないと？
So you're claiming you have no enemies.
いや いないというか…｡
No, I wouldn't say that...
俺の敵は 大体俺です｡
Most of the time, I'm my own worst enemy.
自分の宇宙へ行きたいっていう
夢を➡
The one who delayed my dream of going into space
さんざん邪魔して
足を引っ張り続けたのは➡
結局 俺でした｡
was only me.
I have no other enemies.
他に敵はいません｡
そういうことに
気づかせてくれたのが➡
And the one who helped me realize this
天文学者のシャロンという人です｡
was the astronomer named Sharon.
ビンスさんも彼女に会えば…
敵だとは思わないはずですよ｡
If you get a chance to meet her,
you won't consider her an enemy.
(ﾏｽﾀｰ)いらっしゃい｡
Welcome.
Hmph!
チェッ！俺を置いてきやがって｡
このせっかち野郎が｡
You ditched me, you impatient bastard.
(ピコ)それで このムッタは
何て言ったと思う？
(ビンス)さあ…｡
Guess what Mutta said next...
No clue.
スポンジでタイヤを作ろうと
ぬかしやがった｡
He came up with the idea of using sponge for the tires.
Honestly, I thought he was an idiot at first.
ハッ！正直 初めは
バカかと思ったぜ｡
Using a soft material like sponge wouldn't have occurred to anyone.
強度の弱いスポンジなんて案は
まず出さねえ｡
But it's strong enough to make the short trip from landing site to goal.
ところが 着地からゴールフラッグ
までの距離程度なら➡
十分もつんだ これが｡
And it's easy to prepare spares.
しょうもう
消耗しても
スペアをすぐ用意できやがる｡
Is that why you like Mr. Nanba now?
それでピコは ミスター･ナンバを
気に入ったと？酒に誘うほど…｡
Enough to drink with him?
俺がこんなヤツ
気に入る訳ねえだろ！
How could I ever like this guy?
ただ こいつは こう見えて
失敗に前向きなんだ｡
It's just, he's pretty positive about failure.
And that was...
そこが何か こう…なっ｡
You know?
Only if you're earnest about it.
本気でやった場合に限るよ｡
本気の失敗には価値がある｡
An earnest failure has meaning.
(ビンス)本気の失敗には…➡
An earnest failure
価値がある…か｡
has meaning...
Hey, Vince...
(ピコ)ヘイ ビンス！
Did you cut this up?
これ ピコが切り分けたのか？
きれいに切ったな｡
You did it cleanly.
(ピコ)いや 俺じゃねえ｡リックだ｡
No, it wasn't me... It was Rick.
しょくん
(リック)おはよう諸君！
Morning, friends!
Starting today, we'll begin making our new rocket, Penguin 15!
(リック)今日から 新作ロケット
ペンギン１５号作りだ｡➡
本気でいこう！➡
Let's get serious!
メイン電源オン！
１０･９･８･７･６･５･４･３…➡
Main engine on.
10.
9.
8.
7.
6.
5.
4.
3.
２･１…！
2.
1.
(ﾘｯｸ)また…｡
Oh, not again...
(ﾘｯｸ)昨日のＮＡＳＡチャンネル
見たか？ピコ｡
Were you watching the NASA channel yesterday, Pico?
(ﾋﾟｺ)見たよ｡ブライアンの
宇宙デビュー特集だろ？
You bet.
You mean the special about Brian's space debut, right?
ビンスは？
見たに決まってるだろ｡
How about you, Vince?
Of course I watched it.
Of course!
(ﾘｯｸ)だよな～！
天才過ぎるよ ブライアン！
アメリカ人なのに➡
Brian is such a genius...
An American who completely understands Russian modules!
ロシアのモジュールまで
はあく
ちゃんと把握してるなんて！
Don't shout while you eat, Rick.
(ﾋﾟｺ)食いながら騒ぐな リック｡
飛び散ってるぞ！
You're spitting food everywhere.
《ブライアン･Ｊか…
かっこいいな…》
Brian Jay, huh? He's a cool guy.
僕たちが１５だった この年の秋｡
ブライアンが滞在していた➡
The autumn we were fifteen,
there was trouble at the International Space Station while Brian was aboard.
国際宇宙ステーションで
トラブルが起きた｡
ということで分かったかな？
ここ ﾛｼｱﾓｼﾞｭｰﾙ･ｽﾞｳﾞｪｽﾞﾀでは…｡
Do you understand now?
Here, in the Russian module Zvezda...
Hmm? Hold on.
おい これ！
(撮影者)どうした？
Hey, what's this?
What's wrong?
[TV]地上管制
こちらブライアン･Ｊ｡➡
Ground Control, this is Brian Jay.
ロシアモジュールに
けいほう
警報は出てないか？
Have any warnings been issued for the Russian module?
(管制官)異常はない｡
Everything looks normal.
マジか!?クルーキャビンのあたり
何か燃えてないか？
Seriously?
You're sure nothing is burning near the crew cabin?
(管制官)確認した｡異常はない｡
Confirmed. Everything looks normal.
火が出たら警報が鳴るだろ｡
There would be an alarm if anything were on fire.
(撮影者)火だ！
クルーキャビンからだ！
There's a fire! In the crew cabin!
換気システムとモジュールの
電源を切れ‼➡
Turn off the ventilation and power systems for this module!
Here... This is where the smell's coming from.
にお
ここだ｡ここらが臭うぞ どこだ？
Where's the fire?
こちらもモニターで見てる｡
やはりセンサーの誤作動を疑う｡➡
We're monitoring the situation.
It's possible a sensor has malfunctioned.
こちらでシステムチェックをする｡
(ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)いや 待て！
We'll perform a system check.
No, wait.
見ぃ～っけ！
Found it...
火災は配線の不具合によって
モジュールの裏で起きていた｡➡
The fire was due to a faulty wire in the back of the module.
It could have been a disaster,
だいさんじ
あわや大惨事となる
ところだったが➡
but Brian Jay managed to calmly extinguish the fire.
ブライアン･Ｊが
みきわ
これを冷静に見極め消火｡➡
彼は３０歳の初フライトで
早くも仲間の命を救った｡
On his first flight, at age thirty, he saved the lives of his fellow crew.
ブライアンがさ
初の打ち上げなのに➡
It was hilarious when Brian said he fell asleep during his first launch and didn't remember a thing!
寝ちゃってて
記憶にないって話はウケたなぁ｡
ワクワクしすぎて 前日
全く眠れなかったって あれだろ？
He was so excited, he couldn't sleep the night before, right?
そんな人でも
宇宙飛行士になれんだね｡
Yet he was able to become an astronaut...
I think that Brian's something special.
俺は大物だと思うね
ブライアンは…｡
だって なんか…｡
After all,
俺と同じニオイがする｡
he resembles me!
兄貴のエディ･Ｊん時も
言ってたな それ｡
You said the same thing about his brother, Eddie Jay.
将来 俺が管制官になったら
アポロ１３号みたいな➡
When I become a flight director and there's an accident, like Apollo 13,
事故が起こってもさ
絶対 エディやブライアンを➡
I swear I'll bring Eddie and Brian back safely.
きかん
無事 帰還させてやるね！
ジーン･クランツのように！
Just like Gene Kranz!
管制官に そんな
寝グセの立った奴はいねぇ｡
They won't assign someone with messy hair as flight director.
(ﾘｯｸ)管制室に入る時には直すよ｡
I'll fix it before I enter the control room.
俺は将来 管制官になり➡
In the future, I'll be a flight director,
relaying instructions to the astronaut Vince.
宇宙飛行士になったビンスに
指示を送る｡
そのビンスは
ピコの作った宇宙船に乗る｡
And Vince will be riding in a spaceship Pico built.
さあ立てよ！
ちか
誓いのサイン 今日の分だ｡
Stand up!
Time for today's promise sign.
｢誓いのサイン｣は
僕たち３人の目指す先が➡
The promise sign was meant to symbolize that we three were always aiming for space.
いつも宇宙を向いている
ということを意味した｡
(ﾘｯｸ)今日んとこは帰還するか｡
(ﾋﾟｺ)そこは帰宅でいいだろ
フツーに｡
Time to return to base.
Just say we're going home.
じゃあ！
Bye!
Pothill, Minnesota
僕たちの生まれた町は
ミネソタ州 ポットヒル｡➡
We were born in Pothill, Minnesota.
人口２万の田舎町だ｡
A small town of about twenty thousand.
ポットヒルは郊外に出ると
バカでかい鉱山がある｡➡
Just outside Pothill, there was a huge mine.
鉱山の露天掘りが
この町の生活源であり➡
The strip mine was Pothill's lifeblood,
ポットヒルの男たちの多くは
そこで肉体労働をしている｡➡
and most of the men in Pothill were manual laborers there.
僕の父もピコの父親もそうだ｡
Both my and Pico's fathers were miners.
Hello?
ああ どうしたリック｡
Oh, what is it, Rick?
This Thursday, we'll be able to see the ISS with Brian on board, Vince!
☎(ﾘｯｸ)
アイエスエス
ブライアンの乗ってるＩＳＳ！
木曜に見れるぜ ビンス！
フッ 知ってるよ｡
見に行くに決まってる｡
I know.
I'll be going to watch.
じゃ 木曜に｡
See you on Thursday.
ああ ロケット杉の丘でな｡
Yeah, on Rocket Cedar Hill.
ビンス いつまで続ける気だ？
Vince...
How long are you going to keep making rockets?
例のロケット作り｡
ちゃんと…飛ぶまで｡
Until we make one that flies...
モデルロケットなら
簡単に飛ばせるじゃないか｡➡
It should be simple to make a model rocket that flies.
Why go to all this trouble—
なんで わざわざ難しいものを…｡
紙製のは物足りないんだ｡➡
Paper rockets aren't good enough.
リアルなロケットが作りたい｡
We want to make a real rocket.
お前は将来 何になる気なんだ？
What are your plans for the future?
父さんと同じ鉱山技師に
なるものと思っていたがな｡
I thought you'd become a mining engineer like me...
真面目に将来を考える
時期じゃないのか｡
You're reaching the age where you need to consider your future.
…はい｡
Yes...
(ﾋﾞﾝｽ父)木曜に鉱山で学生向けの
就職説明会がある｡➡
On Thursday, the mine is holding a career fair for students.
You should go after school.
学校が終わったら
お前も見に来なさい｡
木曜はダメだよ 父さん｡
丘でＩＳＳを見る約束があるんだ｡
I can't go Thursday.
I already promised to go to the hill to see the ISS.
Humans have made it to space...
人は宇宙へ行けるというのに…
僕は この町さえ…｡
But I can't even leave this town.
(教師)管制官ってまさか…
ＮＡＳＡにでも行く気か？
A flight director?
Are you planning on joining NASA?
そうです 先生！
ジーン･クランツ 知ってます？
That's right, Teach!
Do you know who Gene Kranz is?
(教師)志望はセントルイス大学？
You're applying to Saint Louis University?
ジーン･クランツの出た大学です｡
そこに行けば…｡
It's Gene Kranz's alma mater.
If I go there...
Hey, Rick!
おい リック！
高望みもいいとこだ｡➡
There's nothing wrong with big dreams,
ポットヒルから こんな大学へ
行けた奴は１人もいない｡
but no one from Pothill has ever been accepted by a university like this.
(教師)お前もか ピコ…
宇宙船を作るだと？➡
You, too, Pico?
You want to build spaceships?
そんなもの 並みの人間に
できることじゃないだろう｡➡
Ordinary people aren't capable of doing that.
並みのお前が口にするな｡
You should think realistically.
全く…｡
Seriously...
自分が何万人に１人の選ばれし
人間だとか思ってんのか？➡
Do you believe yourself to be a one-in-a-million kind of person, Vince?
ビンス 真面目に将来を考えろ｡➡
You have to get serious about your future.
宇宙飛行士なんて
一番 不可能な職業だ｡➡
An astronaut is the last thing you'd ever become.
いくら成績優秀の お前でもな｡
Your excellent grades notwithstanding.
ポットヒルに生まれた時点で
無理だ｡
Once you were born in Pothill, you had no chance.
だまって父親の仕事を
継いだら どうだ｡
Why not follow in your father's footsteps?
その方が親父さんも喜ぶだろ｡
That would make him happy.
ポットヒル工業専門学校へ行け｡
Attend Pothill College of Technology.
将来 鉱山で働けば
十分 安定した人生が送れるぞ｡
If you work in the mines, you'll have a stable life.
なんだよ２人とも 元気ね～な｡
Why are you guys so down?
泣いてんのか？ピコ｡
泣いてねぇよっ！
Are you crying, Pico?
I'm not crying!
(ﾘｯｸ)ＮＡＳＡの技術者
ホーマー･ヒッカムだって➡
Homer Hickam, a NASA engineer, grew up in a tiny town.
最初は田舎町に住んでたんだ｡➡
俺らみたいに 若い頃
ロケットを飛ばしながらさ｡
When he was young, he built rockets the way we do.
だから 気にすんなよ！
So there's nothing to worry about.
ロケットを飛ばしたこともない
せんこう
先公が言ってることなんて！
Who cares what a teacher who's never launched a rocket thinks?
(ﾘｯｸ)それより 本当に大丈夫か？
２人とも｡➡
Anyway, should you guys really be here?
今日の鉱山での説明会…
行くように言われてたんだろ？
Weren't you told to attend the career fair at the mine today?
ここでブライアンのＩＳＳを
見届ける方が➡
It's more important for us to see the ISS and Brian.
俺らにとっては重要だ｡
だよな！
Right!
(ﾘｯｸ)さ そろそろ時間だぞ｡
Okay, it's almost time...
あった！あれだ！
Look! There it is!
(ﾋﾞﾝｽ)あれに…ブライアンが！
Brian is up there...
I get chills when I imagine the people inside...
やっぱ いつ見ても➡
あれに人が乗ってると思うと
ワクワクするよな｡
Yeah...
(ﾘｯｸ)こんな田舎町でも ＩＳＳは
見れるじゃね～か｡なあ！
We live in the middle of nowhere, but we can still see the ISS, right?
誰の頭上にだって
宇宙船は通過するんだ｡
Spaceships fly above each of us.
ピコが新しい宇宙船を作って➡
Pico will build a new spaceship.
ビンスが それに乗ってる｡
Vince will ride inside.
それで俺は…
ビンスに指示を送る！
And I'll
direct the mission!
現在
あれ…どこに入れたっけ？
Huh?
Where'd I put it?
As you place your hopes on the distant moon
And leave on your journey
You smile in spite of your loneliness
Because you believe in yourself
It doesn't matter if your wings don't match
Spread them out
As you
begin your long journey (try now) (try now)
I'm sure you can make it
Please don't hesitate
to move straight forward
You took
all your pain and sorrow (no more) (no more)
And turned it into your strength
So I'm sure even your destiny to fight many a battle
Is on your side
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#59 Promise Sign
Pico and Vince end up going to tech school.
(教師)＜ピコとビンスは
工業専門学校へ行く＞
I've always thought of you as brothers!
(ﾘｯｸ)＜お前らのこと兄弟みたいに
思ってたんだ！＞
(ﾋﾞﾝｽ)＜僕とピコは この日の事を
死ぬほど後悔した＞
Pico and I will regret this day for the rest of our lives.
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Promise Sign"
かお
また
そんな顔して
くちびる
唇
噛み締めて